<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: go | mattyw]]></title>
  <link href="http://mattyw.github.io/blog/categories/go/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mattyw.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-03T19:26:48+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://mattyw.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Williams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[generics and monads in good time]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2015/04/08/generics-and-monads-in-good-time/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-08T09:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2015/04/08/generics-and-monads-in-good-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this blog post I attempt to connect monads in haskell with generics in go, avoiding flame wars as I go.
If I&rsquo;ve made mistakes please let me know and I&rsquo;ll gladly fix them.</p>

<h2>The Thought</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve just finished listening to episode 10 of the <a href="http://bikeshed.fm/10">bikeshed</a> which is
largely a discussion about haskell, and well worth a listen to. However the conversation that starts
at around 29:40 is what triggered this thought.</p>

<h2>Haskell without monads</h2>

<p>If you want to do IO in Haskell you need to use monads. But it&rsquo;s possible to write a number of programs without IO(1).</p>

<p>According to <a href="http://haskell.cs.yale.edu/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/history.pdf">&ldquo;A history of haskell, being lazy with class&rdquo;</a> 6 years passed between the first
release of haskell, and monadic IO being introduced.
Why so long?</p>

<p><strong>The language designers were under no pressure, they had time to think about how IO should be dealt with in the language.</strong></p>

<h2>The question of Go Generics</h2>

<p>Go doesn&rsquo;t support generics, and it&rsquo;s often cited as a big downside or even a failing of the language. However you can still write very useful programs in go
without generics(1). But here&rsquo;s the thing:</p>

<p><strong>The language designers are under no pressure, they have time to think about how generics should be dealt with in the language.</strong></p>

<p>This is important. Just because a language doesn&rsquo;t do something now, doesn&rsquo;t mean it never will.
If you&rsquo;ve not taken a look at go previously because you&rsquo;ve been swayed by the &ldquo;no generics&rdquo; argument I recomend taking a look at go again.</p>

<p>(1) An infinite number for maths fans</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go playground as a service]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/go-playground-as-a-service/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T13:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/go-playground-as-a-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>Update</em></strong>: So I&rsquo;ve learned that there&rsquo;s actually some work to be done here around sandboxing before it&rsquo;s actually ready for public use. Until then I&rsquo;ve removed the server, but the code is still available if you want to play around with it in a trusted setting.</p>

<p>One of the great things about go is the whole environment you get with it, gofmt, godoc, go get. It&rsquo;s all good stuff.
There&rsquo;s also a <a href="http://play.golang.org">playground</a> for you to try things out on.
The docs also have runnable examples in them based off a similar idea:
<a href="http://golang.org/pkg/encoding/json/#example_Unmarshal">http://golang.org/pkg/encoding/json/#example_Unmarshal</a></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a great idea, it means you can actually try the code out while you&rsquo;re reading the docs. But it only works on code from the stdlib. But that makes sense doesn&rsquo;t it? You don&rsquo;t want to allow anyone to import some arbitrary package.</p>

<p>But it occured to me that when someone develops a package, the author might want to include runnable examples for their own code.</p>

<p>The source for something similar to the playgrond is incuded in the go release (misc/goplay) I&rsquo;ve modified it very slightly to allow /compile to be called from any location.
I&rsquo;ve called it <a href="http://github.com/mattyw/goplaas">goplaas</a> (It&rsquo;s not really as a service, but that&rsquo;s the standard suffix these days isn' it? And it got your attention!)</p>

<p>The idea is you install it on your own server, and it will have access to anything installed on your GOPATH. This means you can control what packages can be imported, and also the version.</p>

<p>All you need to do is put some javascript and a textarea into a webpage, point it to your server and you&rsquo;re done.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example using the loggo package from launchpad.net. Try it</p>

<p><code>
I've removed it - sorry
</code></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll try to keep my server running with goplaas for the next few weeks. If it suddenly stops working, it&rsquo;s likely that I&rsquo;ve pulled the server down. You can experiment yourself by running
<code>bash
go install github.com/mattyw/goplaas
./goplaas -http :9999 #Listen on 9999
</code>
goplaas includes a -compile flag for sending compilation instructions to another server, full instructions are in github.</p>

<p>A good next step would be to package this all up into a docker container to allow anyone to install it with relative ease</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojure programming in acme]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2013/10/17/clojure-programming-in-acme/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-17T14:04:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2013/10/17/clojure-programming-in-acme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I finally got round to trying out something i&rsquo;d been meaning to look into for nearly a year, and seeing as clojure and editors seems to be a topic again I thought it would help add some diversity.</p>

<p>Acme is an editor unlike any other. It was designed by Rob Pike for Plan9 (although it&rsquo;s available for unix-like systems using <a href="http://swtch.com/plan9port/">Plan9 from User Space</a>).
It&rsquo;s designed to be an editor and shell. Unlike emacs and vim which encourage you to keep your hands on the keyboard, acme requires use of a 3-button mouse, and it supports something called mouse chording. A rough guide would be:</p>

<ul>
<li>Button 1: Select Text</li>
<li>Button 2: Execute Command</li>
<li>Button 3: Search/ acquire text (or load file)</li>
<li>Button 1-2 Cutting</li>
<li>Button 1-3 Pasting</li>
<li>Button 1-2,3 Cut+Paste (Copy)</li>
</ul>


<p>My introduction to acme was via Russ Cox' video, which is a great starting point:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://mattyw.github.io//www.youtube.com/embed/dP1xVpMPn8M" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>You can probably summarise the whole thing by saying that in acme &ndash; text is data. Once you type some text, it can be saved into a file, executed as a command or passed as an argument to a command.</p>

<p>Obviously this resonated with the clojure part of my brain. It occured to me that being able to select some clojure code in acme and evaluate it would make acme a great editor for clojure.</p>

<p>Thanks to nrepl the job is really quite easy. I wrote a very <em>very</em> simple nrepl client in go. You can find it on my <a href="https://github.com/mattyw/gonrepl">github</a></p>

<p>All it does is read clojure code from stdin and send it to nrepl. This is really all there is to do. In acme you just need to type your command in one of the scratch areas:</p>

<p>Take a look at the below screenshot. You can see:</p>

<ol>
<li>In yellow: selected clojure code with mouse button 1</li>
<li>In red: selected command with mouse button two</li>
<li>Release the buttons and the window in the bottom right contains the evalutated code</li>
</ol>


<p><a href="http://imgur.com/NoEHuqV"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/NoEHuqV.png" title="Hosted by imgur.com" /></a></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a video of me doing it:</p>

<iframe src="http://mattyw.github.io//player.vimeo.com/video/77128688" width="500" height="345" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/77128688">Clojure in Acme</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/user5806599">Matthew Williams</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>

<p>To get this setup yourself:</p>

<ol>
<li>Install plan9 from user space to get acme</li>
<li>run lein repl in some terminal</li>
<li>You&rsquo;ll need a command line tool that can take clojure code on stdin and send it to nrepl. I used my own gonrepl tool- To use that you need to install go then run:</li>
</ol>


<p><code>bash
go install github.com/mattyw/gonrepl/...
</code></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it. Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taming the cloud with juju and raspberry pi]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2013/06/27/taming-the-cloud-with-juju-and-raspberry-pi/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-27T08:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2013/06/27/taming-the-cloud-with-juju-and-raspberry-pi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The idea</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;re going to use a raspberry pi and juju to setup a wordpress blog on aws.</p>

<p>The raspberry pi is an amazing little gadget. Low power enough that I don&rsquo;t feel guilty about leaving it turned on overnight, but flexible enough that I can shove leds into it to grab my attention if needed.</p>

<p><a href="http://juju.ubuntu.com">Juju</a> is ubuntu&rsquo;s answer to setting up services in the cloud. Once installed you simply setup your credentials with an existing cloud provider like aws or hp cloud and then deploy things into it. Setting up wordpress for example is as simple as
<code>bash
juju bootstrap # Setup the cloud environment
juju deploy wordpress # Start an instance and install wordpress on it
juju deploy mysql # Start an instance and install mysql on it
juju add-relation wordpress mysql # Connect wordpress and mysql together
juju expose wordpress #Allow wordpress to be accessed from a public ip
</code></p>

<h2>The Plan</h2>

<ol>
<li>Install go onto the raspberry pi</li>
<li>Install juju</li>
<li>Deploy a wordpress blog</li>
</ol>


<p>We&rsquo;re going to be installing the latest version of juju which is written in go.</p>

<h2>Installing Go</h2>

<p>Dave Cheney has written an excellent article on <a href="http://dave.cheney.net/2012/09/25/installing-go-on-the-raspberry-pi">Installing go on the raspberry pi</a>. On my model B (1.0 revision) I had to update raspi-config so that I could select the 240M/16M memory split, but you might have to see how you get on here. I choose to skip the tests and just ran ./make.bash to build go rather than all.bash.</p>

<p>I was unable to build juju using go 1.0.3. I ended up building go 1.1.1 from source, which seemed to work fine. From memory I believe you need to setup a folder to be your GOPATH before you can install the latest version of go.</p>

<h2>Installing Juju</h2>

<p>Getting the latest tip of juju-core is easy using the go get command, it grabs all the dependencies for you, it does mean we&rsquo;re grabbing tip, but there are ways to fix that later if we need to. juju-core is hosted on launchpad.net which uses bazaar for source control. This means you need to install it before you can run go get. I was able to install it on raspian using
<code>bash
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get bzr
</code>
Without doing the update I was unable to grab all of bzr&rsquo;s dependencies, so I recommend running the update first.</p>

<p>Once bzr is installed you can install juju using go get:
<code>bash
sudo apt-get install libcurl4-gnutls-dev
go get launchpad.net/juju-core/...
</code>
When it&rsquo;s finished you should find a juju binary installed. Mine ended up in my GOPATH, I think because I had something setup wrong somewhere. But if you&rsquo;ve got this far I&rsquo;m sure you&rsquo;ll be able to find it.</p>

<h2>Setting up Juju</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s much better instructions for setting up juju <a href="https://juju.ubuntu.com/get-started/">here</a> The basic steps come down to</p>

<ol>
<li>Setting up a public key</li>
<li>Generating an environments.yaml file</li>
<li>Filling the file in with the data for your cloud provider</li>
</ol>


<p>I configured juju for aws. My ~/.juju/environments.yaml file looked like this:
```yaml
default: amazon
environments:
  amazon:</p>

<pre><code>type: ec2
  access-key: MY AWS ACCESS KEY
  secret-key: MY AWS SECRET KEY
  control-bucket: mattyw-ec2-bucket
  admin-secret: mattyw-ec2-admin
</code></pre>

<p>```
Once you&rsquo;ve done this, try running <strong>juju bootstrap</strong>. If it finishes without error wait a minute or so and run <strong>juju status</strong>, If all goes well you should see something like this</p>

<p>```yaml
$ juju status
machines:
  &ldquo;0&rdquo;:</p>

<pre><code>agent-state: started
agent-version: 1.11.0
dns-name: ec2-23-20-228-111.compute-1.amazonaws.com
instance-id: i-0bfc3d64
series: precise
</code></pre>

<p>services: {}
```</p>

<p>Now we can start the business of getting a blog up and running:</p>

<p><code>bash
juju deploy wordpress
juju deploy mysql
juju add-relation wordpress mysql
juju expose wordpress
</code>
You might have to wait a few minutes for everything to start up, keep taking a look at the output of <strong>juju status</strong> until you see all the agent-states running and expose true on wordpress.</p>

<p>When it&rsquo;s done you should see something like this in your juju status output:
```yaml
 wordpress:</p>

<pre><code>charm: cs:precise/wordpress-15
exposed: true
relations:
  db:
  - mysql
  loadbalancer:
  - wordpress
units:
  wordpress/0:
    agent-state: started
    agent-version: 1.11.0
    machine: "1"
    public-address: ec2-54-234-76-38.compute-1.amazonaws.com
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Now point your web browser to the url in public-address and there you go, you&rsquo;re deploying stuff from your pi.</p>

<p>Juju doesn&rsquo;t stop at just deploying blogs. Check out <a href="http://juju.ubuntu.com">Juju</a> to see what else it can do for you</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[why I like elixir (and other go programmers might too)]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2013/06/17/why-i-like-elixir/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-17T21:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattyw.github.io/blog/2013/06/17/why-i-like-elixir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>My journey to elixir</h2>

<p>Erlang was the first functional language I ever used. When I first started reading <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/jaerlang/programming-erlang">Programming Erlang</a> by Joe Armstrong I was hooked, I was fascinated in a language where &ldquo;=&rdquo; didn&rsquo;t indicate an assignment, and the idea of pattern matching immediately struck a chord with me, I loved the one module per &lsquo;process&rsquo; thing. Erlang was set to become my favourite language, there was only one problem.</p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t like the syntax</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a completely personal view, I know people who love the syntax, I just didn&rsquo;t. To me it just didn&rsquo;t have what Christopher Alexander in &ldquo;The Timeless way of building&rdquo; calls &ldquo;quality without a name&rdquo;. I suppose I just didn&rsquo;t find it fun to type. So after re writing a couple of internal libraries in erlang to see what they looked like (they were much shorter and quite easy to read) I stopped using it, and started playing around with other languages like haskell and clojure.</p>

<p>Clojure was my first lisp dialect and I enjoy it alot, the syntax, the whole homoiconicity thing, macro&rsquo;s aren&rsquo;t something you should use all the time &ndash; but it&rsquo;s comforting to know they&rsquo;re there to fall back on if you need them.</p>

<p>Parallel to this functional language experimentation was another path &ndash; languages I used at work, which has seen me recently move from writing mostly in Python to Go. Go&rsquo;s channels and go routines are great, but when I started writing go code seriously (about 8 months ago) there was something that immediately stuck me.</p>

<p>```go
thing, err := someFunction()
if err != nil {</p>

<pre><code>//handle the error
</code></pre>

<p>}
```
Now, I&rsquo;m not going to start complaining about go&rsquo;s error handling, because I like it. But sometimes I would like to be able to make use of pattern matching and do something like this:</p>

<p><code>go
{thing, nil} = someFunction()
</code></p>

<p>And have my goroutine just dies if it fails. I know that&rsquo;s not go&rsquo;s philosophy with errors, and that&rsquo;s fine. I&rsquo;m just saying.</p>

<h2>Work and Fun Collide</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve spent the past 6 months saying to people that I would like a lisp dialect to be built onto go. What I really meant was I wanted a language that would let me do go style concurrency and play around with a repl, macros and all that functional programming <em>fun</em> stuff.</p>

<p>It looks to me that elixir provides exactly that.</p>

<p>Just look at these two programs. Both call a 10 second sleeping function on a seperate &lsquo;thread&rsquo; and wait for the response. The first in go, the second in elixir.
```go
package main</p>

<p>import (</p>

<pre><code>"fmt"
"time"
</code></pre>

<p>)</p>

<p>func longRun(response chan string) {</p>

<pre><code>time.Sleep(10e9)
response &lt;- "done"
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>func main() {</p>

<pre><code>response := make(chan string)
go longRun(response)
value := &lt;-response
fmt.Println(value)
</code></pre>

<p>}
<code>
</code>elixir
defmodule Main do</p>

<p>  def longRun(pid) do</p>

<pre><code>:timer.sleep(10000)
pid &lt;- {:result, :done}
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def main() do</p>

<pre><code>spawn(__MODULE__, :longRun, [self])
receive do
  {:result, value} -&gt;
    IO.puts value
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>Main.main()
```</p>

<p>They&rsquo;re not too different, elixir has spawn where go has &lsquo;go&rsquo; and elxir has receive where go has select. There&rsquo;s no denying that they&rsquo;re completely different languages, in some rather crude tests I&rsquo;ve done go does seem to be largely faster, but elixir let&rsquo;s me do meta-programming whilst forgetting about types.</p>

<p>I expect to be blogging alot more about elixir in the future</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
